<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
/*
 *                Doelan development code
 *
 * This code may be freely distributed and modified under the
 * terms of the GNU General Public Licence.  This should
 * be distributed with the code. If you do not have a copy,
 * see:
 *
 *      http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.txt
 *
 * Copyright (c) 2004-2005 ENS Microarray Platform
 * Copyright for this code is held jointly by the individual
 * authors.  These should be listed in @author doc comments.
 *
 * For more information on the Doelan project and its aims,
 * or to join the Doelan mailing list, visit the home page
 * at:
 *
 *      http://www.transcriptome.ens.fr/doelan
 */
 -->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Welcome to Doelan</title>
    <author email="jourdren@biologie.ens.fr">Laurent Jourdren</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

         
    <section name="Welcome to Doelan">

    <div style="float: right; margin: 0 10px 20px 20px; padding: 5px; border: 1px solid #999; background-color: #eee;">
        <h5 style="margin: 0; font-size: smaller; border-bottom: 1px solid #aaaaaa">Get Doelan 1.0.1</h5>
        <p style="font-size: smaller">
	<img valign="top" src="http://maven.apache.org/images/folder-open.gif" border="0" alt="" title="download"/>
          <a href="download.html">Download</a> Doelan 1.0.1<br/>
	</p>
        <ul style="margin-top: 0; list-style-type: disc">
          <li style="font-size: smaller"><a href="download.html#requirements">System Requirements</a></li>
	  <li style="font-size: smaller"><a href="installing.html">Installation Instructions</a></li>
          <li style="font-size: smaller"><a href="quickstart.html">QuickStart tutorial</a></li>
        </ul>
     </div>
      
    

		<p>Doelan is an automated tool to check the quality 
		of produced DNA microarrays. This software is based on the execution 
		of TestSuites on quality control data to validate batches of chips. 
		The reports generated by Doelan will help microarray platforms in 
		their quality approach such as ISO 9001 certification. Doelan 
		application is written with Java programming language, works with a 
		plug-in system that allows everyone to add is own validation test and 
		is distributed under the <a href="license.html">GNU General Public License</a>.</p>

		<p>Production of 
		glass slide microarrays requires the spotting of a large number of 
		probes. In this process, many factors can influence the success of 
		the spotting (i.e. blocked spotting pin, glass slides...); so 
		controlling the quality of the spotting process is a required step 
		before to distribute chips to the user. Up to now, it was quite 
		difficult for the quality control manager to check if the spotting of 
		chips was good or bad: many different parameters as spot diameters, 
		heterogeneous spots or absent spots had to be manually considered to 
		reach a decision. In addition, it is a very subjective step, so that 
		the opinion about a batch may differ between two quality control 
		managers. Using manually defined criterias for microarray quality, 
		Doelan allows an automated expertise of the quality of a batch of 
		slides and makes automatically the decision of validation or 
		rejection of the batch.</p> 

		<p>The principle of Doelan is based on 
		TestSuites. A TestSuite is a set of tests, which are dedicated to a 
		specific features (for example spot diameter). The microarray 
		designer creates the TestSuites and sets the parameters (i.e. 
		minimal and maximal values, thresholds...) of each test to validate a 
		chip. Several TestSuites can be created according to the type of 
		validation experiment chosen as sybergreen, universal RNA 
		hybridisation or a "real" experiment. The fail of one of the tests 
		leads to the fail of the TestSuite, and consequently to the rejection 
		of all the batch of chips. Doelan is bundled with many tests. These 
		tests can deal with various features of the chips such as spot 
		diameter, spot flags, spot heterogeneity, saturated pixels of the 
		spots... In addition to this standard tests, the Doelan plug-in 
		system with Java programming allows one to set up new kind of test to 
		fulfil specific needs.</p>

	</section>

  </body>
</document>
